Finding Aid for David E. Mattern papers, 1905-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David E. Mattern papers 1905-1972, 1930-1959
Mattern, David E., 1890-1959.
(in 5 boxes)
3.5 linear feet
851840 Aa 2
Professor of music education at University of Michigan. Correspondence relating to his work in music education; also programs relating to music education, particularly the Summer Conference on Music Education; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mattern's wife, Viola Mattern (donor no. 3564 ) in 1959 and 1964, and by his daughter, Shirley Smith (donor no. 7990 ) in November, 1991.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
David Earl Mattern was a professor of Music Education in the School of Music at the University of Michigan from 1929 to his death in 1959. His career spanned forty years, with activities ranging from playing first violin for the Rochester Philharmonic Orchestra to conducting the University of Michigan's "Under and Over Sixty Club."
Born in 1890, Mattern was a 1906 graduate of Newton High School in Newton, Iowa. The proof from his 1957 entry in Who's Who in America provides a detailed outline of his education and stages of his career. Mattern married Viola Smith on April 21, 1924, and Shirley Mattern (later Mrs. Haldon Smith) was born to them in 1925.
Early in his career, Mattern taught summer session instruction of violin classes at Cornell, the Eastman School of Music, and Ithaca College. In 1926, he moved to Grand Rapids, Michigan, to become the supervisor of music for the public schools. During his three years in Grand Rapids, he also conducted the Schubert Club, a large male chorus.
In 1929, Mattern was offered a position at the University of Michigan in the area of music education. From 1929 to 1931, he conducted the University Symphony Orchestra, and from 1931 to 1947, he was the director of the Men's Glee Club. Mattern was also involved as the director of music for the University School in the School of Education beginning in 1931.
Mattern's interest in music education reached beyond a person's formal school years, leading him to take on a position as director of the Detroit Extension Orchestra. This program, administered by the University's Extension Service, allowed adult residents of the southeast corner of the state to gather and participate in high quality amateur performances. The orchestra's repertoire included the masters and the classics.
Mattern was associated professionally with the: [Michigan] State Committee on Creative Arts, Michigan String Quartet Festivals, Music Teachers' National Association, Music Educator's National Conference, [Michigan] State Advisory Council on Music Education, and the Michigan School Band and Orchestra Association.
David Mattern died April 14, 1959.
The David Earl Mattern Papers document Mattern's education and career from 1905 to his death in 1959. The collection is organized in four series: Biographical and Personal Materials, Education, Professional Career, and Photographs. Topics covered extensively in this collection include the University of Michigan Men's Glee Club, the Extension Orchestra, and Mattern's activities during the university's Summer Session.
Subjects:
Mattern, David Earl, 1890-1959.; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Men's Glee Club.; University of Michigan. School of Music.; University of Michigan. Summer Session.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Grand Rapids High School (Mich.). Band.; Mattern, David Earl, 1890-1959.; Music ensembles.; Orchestras.; Sousa, John Philip, 1854-1932.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Men's Glee Club.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical and Personal Materials 1931-1972
  The Biographical and Personal Materials series contains several biographical articles. Also included are other personal papers relating to the purchase of a lot, and the settling of his estate after his death. In 1972, Merle Hanson, a doctoral candidate in the School of Music, requested Viola Mattern's and Shirley Smith's permission to base his dissertation on Professor Mattern's career, and his proposal is included here.
  - Clippings and Articles (Box 1)
  - Green Scrapbook 1926-1929 (Box 1)
  - Red Scrapbook 1923-1928 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1929-1959 (Box 2)
  - Green Scrapbook 1921-1926 (Box 2)
  - Black Scrapbook 1922-1928 (Box 2)
- Education
  Education consists of grade cards from Mattern's late high school years, some class notes from Cornell, and his summer session degree in music for public schools.
  - Miscellaneous 1905-1912 (Box 3)
  - Class notes undated (Box 3)
- Professional Career
  The Professional Career series begins with papers about Mattern's early work in Pennsylvania, teaching and playing professionally, and his work in the mid 1920s in Kalamazoo and Grand Rapids. These are followed by copies of Mattern's numerous publications, speeches and lectures. Mattern was very active in the University of Michigan Symphony Orchestra in the 1930s, and the Michigan School Band and Orchestra Association throughout his time at the University.
  Within this series are six folders relating to Mattern's work with the U of M Men's Glee Club, which he conducted from 1931 to 1947. Included are programs, clippings and business materials, also two folders of letters from men of the Glee Club serving in the armed forced during World War II.
  Mattern's involvement in the University Extension Orchestra is also documented in the Professional Career series. Beside the programs, business correspondence and clippings, there is a folder of letters from the participants in the orchestra, many of which are not dated. The Summer Sessions files relates to arrangements for summer instructors for music education classes at the University of Michigan. These have been arranged chronologically.
  - Pennsylvania Summer Sessions 1917-1924 (Box 3)
  - Rochester Philharmonic Orchestra 1920s (Box 3)
  - Junior and Senior High conducting 1917-1928 (Box 3)
  - Kalamazoo Symphony Orchestra, Saginaw Civic Orchestra, Schubert Club of Grand Rapids (Box 3)
  - Publications 1928-1953 (Box 3)
  - Lectures for C201, C211, C41, C50 classes 1941, 1950 undated (Box 3)
  - Lectures for C63 undated (Box 3)
  - Speeches (?) undated (Box 3)
  - Mattern's "Cookbook" (Box 3)
  - Michigan School Band and Orchestra Association, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - U of M Symphony Orchestra 1930-1933 (Box 3)
  - U of M Men's Glee Club
    - Programs (Box 3)
    - Clippings and Publicity (Box 3)
    - Business (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Soldiers' Letters, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - U of M Extension Orchestra
    - Programs 1945-1959 (Box 4)
    - Participants' Letters (Box 4)
    - Business and Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Clippings and Publicity (Box 4)
  - U of M "Under and Over Sixty Club" 1956 (Box 4)
  - U of M Summer Sessions
    - 1936, 1939, 1947-1949 (Box 4)
    - 1950 (Box 4)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 4)
    - 1953-1956 (Box 4)
    - 1955 (Box 4)
  - Guest and Church conducting (Box 5)
  - Programs Attended (Box 5)
- Photographs
  - Portraits (Box 5)